I was never a distance
runner, but I sure can sprint.
This is Higher Ed Hot
takes, and I'm Joel Goodman.
Across the globe, universities
are facing increased pressure.
Enrollment is down, inflation is up.
Governments are taking openly hostile
actions against higher education, and
the ultimate result is that people are
losing their jobs due to both staffing
reductions and institutional closings.
I personally survived a
round of redundancies in 2009
during my first higher ed job.
I can still remember the
fear, dread, and stress.
I remember colleagues unceremoniously
being let go with little regard
for their humanity and even
less for their years of service.
And like everything, this
all comes back to money.
The lack of it to be more specific.
To be even more specific, this
all lands on ego and the misguided
thinking that a few lapses here
and there don't amount to much.
You know, choosing to paint residence
halls every other summer rather
than give incoming and returning
students a clean place to live.
Spending hundreds of thousands on a
new student information system with no
student input on the user experience.
Always a successful choice.
Right?
And of course, my favorite
choosing to ignore your
institution's website performance.
The lowest of low hanging fruit that
costs little to no money and returns
immediate value is often ignored
for the sake of someone's bad taste.
According to Bravery Media's April,
2025, speedy U benchmarking data.
46% of higher ed websites in the
US are operating at 70% or less
of their optimal performance.
For the UK and Canada, it's 65%.
For New Zealand, 64, Ireland, 78%, and for
Australia, a whopping 83% of all of their
higher ed websites are slow, slow, slow.
70% of their optimal performance.
If you want, you can do some fancy math
to figure out how many clicks from display
ads you're wasting money on because they
get to your site and immediately leave.
But I'll summarize things this way.
A Google study showed that
53% - over half- of your mobile
visitors will leave your website
if it takes three seconds to load.
Every 100 milliseconds beyond that
can add another 1% onto the number.
To put that in perspective, most
schools are leaving millions
in potential tuition revenue on
the table in order to look cool.
Like, forget the table.
They're throwing that money on the
floor, stepping on it over and over
and over again because someone who
is not a designer, not a developer,
not a marketer, wants a campus drone
video on the homepage or a newsfeed
or an anthem video, whatever that is.
They're trying and failing to look
cool and it's costing your institution.
It's costing real money.
The people you are trying to
engage with a fancy website don't
even wait around for it to load.
They never even see it.
I've been nice and professional
about this for a few years, but
we're kind of in critical times now.
Our institutions are failing, closing.
We're cutting hundreds of jobs.
We're overworking our staff,
raising performance expectations
while decreasing their resources.
Does a faster website fix this?
No.
Pro, probably not completely, but
a couple mil extra to the bottom
line, certainly couldn't hurt.
This is a stewardship issue, and I
suppose it's also an educational one,
but we have to get our houses in order.
Money keeps getting spent and
wasted on software and campaigns
and ads and new initiatives that
are all going to perform below their
potential because your website's slow.
That's what's funny.
I, I mean, not funny ha ha, but really,
you know, funny, sad, it's that we can't
see the forest for the trees despite all
the information being available to us.
We let our industry an important
world changing sector wither
because we forget that we can
ask our audiences how this works.
We accidentally yet actively work to
undermine our universities because
we're easily distracted by sales
pitches and demos and typically not
informed enough to make smart decisions.
It's a real problem and it seems to
be endemic to higher ed globally.
I would be remiss if I acted like
this was just about slow websites, but
it's also about student experiences,
alumni and donor relations, and
our communication strategies.
No, it's not just slow websites
that are the problem, but
it is a perfect case study.
So what can you do about it?
Well, a whole lot actually, and it
doesn't even have to cost you very much.
If you have developers on staff, it
could cost you next to nothing, honestly.
But after years of tracking and fixing
this stuff at Bravery Media, I can
pinpoint some common issues to look at.
And please, you can reach out to
me if you need more specifics.
That's what I'm here for.
First off, big videos.
Get rid of them and if you're not gonna
get rid of them, you need to serve
them from a media streaming CDN, with
different sizes for different devices.
But no one who matters is actually
watching your homepage background video.
I'm sorry, they're just not.
And if you're going to embed videos
from somewhere else, make sure it's not
loading duplicate JavaScript for each one.
YouTube loves to do that, and
it makes your webpage slow.
Here's one, you're not
gonna like tracking pixels.
Why are you loading Facebook pixels
all over your website when nearly
zero Gen Alpha kids use meta products?
I. Those tracking pixels slow down
your website's loading time and
actively hurt your conversion rate.
It's ironic that the thing meant to track
how performant your paid ads are actually
make your paid ads less efficient, huh?
Ironic or purposeful.
I, but I'll let you be the judge of that.
Attribution is nearly impossible
today anyway, so find better, more
native ways of gaining insight about
your users than loading up your
website with third party trackers.
This is the single biggest contributor
to double digit load times, and it's
costing you applicants and donors.
Next, you need to modernize your code.
I won't get too technical, but I still
see so many implementations of Bootstrap
in higher ed, jQuery in use and content
management systems that are outdated and
built on web standards from the nineties.
Friends.
Your website can look unique
and express your brand promise
without being gigantic and slow.
But the truth is most of our
websites look the same anyway.
If you want an immediate edge in
higher ed marketing performance,
make your website blazing fast.
Performance is non-negotiable when
it comes to web marketing, but every
level from the website up to the paid
ads has to commit to that performance.
Otherwise, the weakest link
brings all the rest down.
Since early 2024, my agency,
Bravery Media, has been running
speed and accessibility tests
on your website every week.
Seriously, we have nearly every
institution in the us, Canada,
uk, Ireland, Australia, and New
Zealand, tracked on speedyu.com
so you can see where you rank
among your peer institutions.
If you want a deeper dive into
your website's performance and
specific fixes, let's talk.
I can create a checklist for
your dev team, or we can help
improve your website for you.
But I can't say it enough.
This is the single most value
packed thing you could do.
It costs so little and returns so
much that it's irresponsible not to
optimize your website's performance.